Henry R. Seager research notes and monographs 5249
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Henry R. Seager research notes and monographs
1890-1930
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Seager, Henry R.
5249
0.33 cubic feet
0.3 linear ft.
Lecture notes, manuscripts (documents), reprints.
Files dealing with union difficulties with Communism during World War II and the McCarthy era.
2293771
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, November 01, 2007
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, February 22, 2017
Biographical / Historical
Seager, Henry Rogers (July 21, l870-Aug. 23, 1930), economist, was born in Lansing, Michigan, the son of
Schuyler Fiske Seager, a lawyer, and Alice (Berry) Seager. Graduating at the University of Michigan in 1890, he did further work during the succeeding years at the Johns Hopkins University, at the Universities of Halle, Berlin, and Vienna, and at the University of Pennsylvania, where he received the Ph.D. degree in 1894. That year he was appointed instructor in economics in the Wharton School of Finance and Commerce, and in 1896 he was made an assistant professor; in 1902 he became adjunct professor and in 1905, professor, in Columbia University, where he served till death. On June 5, 1899, he was married to Harriet Henderson of Philadelphia who died in 19285 their son survived him.
Seager's training as an economist was in English classicism, in the German historical method and in the peculiar Austrian approach. His published work shows clearly the influence of each. His greatest admiration was for Simon N. Patten (q.v.), with whom he served at the University of Pennsylvania but whose influence on his thought was slight. Seager's mind was orderly and compressive rather than brilliant and generalizing; conservatism was perhaps its distinguishing characteristic. He was solid and patient, slow to conclude, and even slower to write his conclusions. One result of this was that he was less a writing scholar than one who worked with students. Literally hundreds of dissertations passed through his careful hands at Columbia and many generations of students heard his lectures on labor and on corporation problems. Always active in meliorative activities, he assisted materially in the establishment of a system of workmen's compen-sation in New York; he was a supporter of the Survey (formerly Charities and the Commons) and for many years a member of its board of directors. During the war he served as secretary of the Shipbuilding Labor Adjustment Board, and in 1919-20, he was executive secretary of the President's Second Industrial Conference. He was one of the founders and three times president of i the American Association for Labor Legislation. He was frequently consulted by philanthropists, legislators and publicists; he was a member of the editorial board ) of The Political Science Quarterly, and in 1922 was
president of the American Economic Association. In all these varied activities he had one purpose: to better social conditions within the framework of laissez-faire. He possessed a determined faith that this could be done and worked constantly to show the way. Melioration consisted in making changes here and there, which while not disturbing fundamental arrangements, reduced their burden on less favored individuals. Improvement consisted in legal change and a large part of his effort was always directed toward reform by legislation.
His most considerable work is Principles of Economics, first published under this title in 1913, which grew out of his Introduction to Economics (1904 and later editions) and appeared in its final form in 1923. The most important of his other writings are Trust and Corporation Problems (1929), with C.A. Gulick, Jr. and the posthumous volume, Labor and Other Economic Essays (l93l), to which is attached his complete bibliography. Somewhat more than the final half of the Principles of Economics is devoted to essays on important problems: banking, the tariff, railroads, trusts, taxation, labor and social insurance. The theoretical section begins with a consideration of consumption, progresses through value and production, and ends with distribution. There were many books published during this period with much the same outline; but Seager's was characterized by emphasis on all that pertained to human welfare. This led to stress on consumption and on the demand side of the value equilibrium, as well as to extra consideration of monopoly gains. The discussion of distribution was carried out within the framework of the "specific productivity" analysis but with more than usual weight given to such subjective influences as the balancing, in consumers' and producers' minds, of marginal disutilities over against marginal utilities. The conclusions were usually optimistic. Seager believed in progress and believed that, under the going system, it was being achieved. He felt, for instance, that capital goods were multiplying more rapidly than population and that this would tend to raise standards of living. He did not believe, however, that the possibilities of progress which inhere in the system insure automatic betterment. Groups of interested people, with journals and propaganda, need to be vigilant in the public interest. This duty of the good citizen, as Seager saw it, was best exemplified In his own career. He never became aware of a duty
that he did not forthwith perform. In his posthumous Labor and Other Economic Essays his program is outlined: "The two great objects to be aimed at are: 1. To protect wage-earners in the continued enjoyment of standards of living to which they are already accustomed. II. To assist them to attain to higher standards of living" (p.131). The contingencies which were the principal threats to existing standards were "(I) industrial accidents, (2) illness, (3) invalidity and old age, (4) premature death, (5) unemployment" (ibid.) All these, Seager felt, were legitimate objects of collective action. As for raising standards, this was largely dependent on industrial advance and on better education.
To all persons of Seager's generation the rather I sudden rise of a complete alternative system in Russia offered a shock to which adjustment was necessarily slow. Because everything there was so antithetical to the system to which so many theoretical hostages had been given, the immediate impulse was to belittle Soviet accomplishments. Seager was exposed to the full force of the new ideas. Gradually they gained weight in his mind until at last his essential honesty compelled, not acceptance, but exploration. In 1930, with a group of companions, he undertook a Journey to the scene of these new economic adventures, in the midst of which he was taken ill. He died in Kiev of pneumonia, August 23, 1930. He was thus lost to the world at the close of an old period and the beginning of a new one. His Identification with economy of the opening decades of the nineteenth century was a fortuitous one, but his progress into the new years cannot be said to have fairly started. He remains an economist of laissez-faire, of more than usual significance in foreshadowing the ameliorative program which so soon became a center of Interest.
Scope and Contents
Collection includes Seager's manuscript notes on introductory lectures in political economy, delivered by Professor Richard Theodore Ely (Johns Hopkins University, 1890). These include sections on the growth of economic theory in modern civilization, functions of government, economic ideals, socialism, and political science; Seager's manuscript notes on the "Essential Principles of Administration" and data on private law, civilian vs. public rights, and state vs. federal authority, the theory of division of power, and judicial acts of administration; also reprints of Seager's writings (1902-1923) including works on administration, anti-trust law, economics, prosperity, company unions and trade-unions, minimum wage, wage adjustment, employment agencies, unemployment, interest rates, government labor policy, the courts and labor law; and Seager's necrology.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Antitrust law -- United States; Business cycles.; Company unions -- United States; Comparative economics.; Comparative government.; Employment agencies -- United States; Federal-state controversies -- United States; Labor laws and legislation--United States.; Labor policy -- United States; Political science.; Economics teachers.; Lobbyists.; Wages. Minimum wage. United States.; Ely, Richard T. (Richard Theodore), 1854-1943; Seager, Henry R. (Henry Roger), 1870-1930
2293771
- The Impatience Theory of Interest, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Reprinted from the American Economic Review, v.2:no.4 (1912:Dec.)
  - Item 1: The Theory of The Minimun Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Author: Henry R. Seager
    Notes: Address given at the Sixth Annual Meeting ot the American Association for Labor Legislation, Boston, Dec. 28, 1912
    Format: Publication
    Language: English.
  - Item 2: The Theory of The Minimum Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Notes: Address given at the Sixth Annual Meeting ot the American Association for Labor Legislation, Boston, Dec. 28, 1912, Second copy
  - Item 3: The New Anti-Trust Acts, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Notes: Reprinted fro Political Science Quarterly, v.30:no.3 (1915:Sept.)
  - Item 4: Unemployment: Problem and Remedies, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Notes: Reprints and Reports and Addresses of the National Conference of Charities and Correction, no.42.
  - Item 5: Coordination of Federal, State and Municipal, Employment Bureaus, 1918; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Notes: Reprinted from the American Economic Review Supplement, v.8:no.1 (1918:March)
  - Item 6: Effect of Present Methods on Future Wage Adjustments, 1919; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Notes: Reprinted from the Proceedings of the Academy of Political Science, v.8:no.2 (1919:Feb.)
  - Item 7: The Recent Trust Decisions, 1911; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Notes: Advance Sheets from Political Science Quarterly, v.26:no.4 (1911:Dec.)
  - Item 8: The Impatience Theory of Interest, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Notes: Reprinted from the American Economic Review, v.2:no.4 (1912:Dec.)
- The Attitude of American Courts Towards Restrictive Labor Laws, 1904; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Reprinted from Political Science Quarterly, v.19:no.4
  - Item 1: Professor Patten's Theory of Prosperity, 1902; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Notes: no. 333. Reprinted from the Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science for March, 1902
  - Item 2: The Attitude of American Courts Towards Restrictive Labor Laws, 1904; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Notes: Reprinted from Political Science Quarterly, v.19:no.4
  - Item 3: Public Expenditures and Public Revenues; and Taxation and Tax Reform in the United States, 1905; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Notes: Chapters added to Seager's Introduction to Economics: Third Edition, Revised and Enlarged
  - Item 4: The Attitude of the State Towards Trade Unions and Trusts, 1907; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Notes: Reprinted from Political Science Quarterly, v.22:no.3
  - Item 5: The Legal Status of Trade Unions in the United Kingdom, with Conclusions Applicable to the United States, 1907; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Notes: Reprinted from Political Science Quarterly, v.22:no.4
- Public Expenditures and Public Revenues; and Taxation and Tax Reform in the United States, 1905; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Chapters added to Seager's Introduction to Economics: Third Edition, Revised and Enlarged
  - Item 1: Professor Patten's Theory of Prosperity, 1902; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 2: The Attitude of American Courts Towards Restrictive Labor Laws, 1904; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 3: Public Expenditures and Public Revenues; and Taxation and Tax Reform in the United States, 1905; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 4: The Attitude of the State Towards Trade Unions and Trusts, 1907; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 5: The Legal Status of Trade Unions in the United Kingdom, with Conclusions Applicable to the United States, 1907; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
- The Attitude of the State Towards Trade Unions and Trusts, 1907; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Reprinted from Political Science Quarterly, v.22:no.3
  - Item 1: Professor Patten's Theory of Prosperity, 1902; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 2: The Attitude of American Courts Towards Restrictive Labor Laws, 1904; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 3: Public Expenditures and Public Revenues; and Taxation and Tax Reform in the United States, 1905; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 4: The Attitude of the State Towards Trade Unions and Trusts, 1907; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 5: The Legal Status of Trade Unions in the United Kingdom, with Conclusions Applicable to the United States, 1907; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
- The Legal Status of Trade Unions in the United Kingdom, with Conclusions Applicable to the United States, 1907; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Reprinted from Political Science Quarterly, v.22:no.4
  - Item 1: Professor Patten's Theory of Prosperity, 1902; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 2: The Attitude of American Courts Towards Restrictive Labor Laws, 1904; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 3: Public Expenditures and Public Revenues; and Taxation and Tax Reform in the United States, 1905; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 4: The Attitude of the State Towards Trade Unions and Trusts, 1907; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 5: The Legal Status of Trade Unions in the United Kingdom, with Conclusions Applicable to the United States, 1907; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Company Unions vs. Trade Unions, 1923; Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Reprinted from the American Economic Review, v.13:no.1 (1923:March).
  - Item 1: Company Unions vs. Trade Unions, 1923; Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Notes: Reprinted from the American Economic Review, v.13:no.1 (1923:March).
  - Item 2: Henry Rogers Seager, 1930; Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Author: Samuel McCune Lindasy; H. E. Hoagland; Charles A. Gulick, jr.
    Notes: Reprinted from American Economic Reivew, v.20:no.4 (1930:Dec.)
  - Item 3: Henry Rogers Seager, 1870-1930, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Author: Samuel McCune Lindsay
    Notes: Reprinted from the Columbia University Quarterly, Dec. 1930.
- Henry Rogers Seager, 1930; Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Reprinted from American Economic Reivew, v.20:no.4 (1930:Dec.)
  - Item 1: Company Unions vs. Trade Unions, 1923; Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 2: Henry Rogers Seager, 1930; Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 3: Henry Rogers Seager, 1870-1930, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Professor Patten's Theory of Prosperity, 1902; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  no. 333. Reprinted from the Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science for March, 1902
  - Item 1: Professor Patten's Theory of Prosperity, 1902; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 2: The Attitude of American Courts Towards Restrictive Labor Laws, 1904; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 3: Public Expenditures and Public Revenues; and Taxation and Tax Reform in the United States, 1905; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 4: The Attitude of the State Towards Trade Unions and Trusts, 1907; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Item 5: The Legal Status of Trade Unions in the United Kingdom, with Conclusions Applicable to the United States, 1907; Publication (Box 1, Folder 1)
- The Recent Trust Decisions, 1911; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Advance Sheets from Political Science Quarterly, v.26:no.4 (1911:Dec.)
  - Item 1: The Theory of The Minimun Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 2: The Theory of The Minimum Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 3: The New Anti-Trust Acts, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 4: Unemployment: Problem and Remedies, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 5: Coordination of Federal, State and Municipal, Employment Bureaus, 1918; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 6: Effect of Present Methods on Future Wage Adjustments, 1919; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 7: The Recent Trust Decisions, 1911; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 8: The Impatience Theory of Interest, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Notes, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Undated. No title. Bound.
  - Item 1: Notes, Publication (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Notes: Undated. No title. Bound.
- The Theory of The Minimun Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Address given at the Sixth Annual Meeting ot the American Association for Labor Legislation, Boston, Dec. 28, 1912
  - Item 1: The Theory of The Minimun Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 2: The Theory of The Minimum Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 3: The New Anti-Trust Acts, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 4: Unemployment: Problem and Remedies, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 5: Coordination of Federal, State and Municipal, Employment Bureaus, 1918; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 6: Effect of Present Methods on Future Wage Adjustments, 1919; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 7: The Recent Trust Decisions, 1911; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 8: The Impatience Theory of Interest, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
- The Theory of The Minimum Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Address given at the Sixth Annual Meeting ot the American Association for Labor Legislation, Boston, Dec. 28, 1912, Second copy
  - Item 1: The Theory of The Minimun Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 2: The Theory of The Minimum Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 3: The New Anti-Trust Acts, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 4: Unemployment: Problem and Remedies, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 5: Coordination of Federal, State and Municipal, Employment Bureaus, 1918; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 6: Effect of Present Methods on Future Wage Adjustments, 1919; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 7: The Recent Trust Decisions, 1911; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 8: The Impatience Theory of Interest, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
- The New Anti-Trust Acts, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Reprinted fro Political Science Quarterly, v.30:no.3 (1915:Sept.)
  - Item 1: The Theory of The Minimun Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 2: The Theory of The Minimum Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 3: The New Anti-Trust Acts, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 4: Unemployment: Problem and Remedies, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 5: Coordination of Federal, State and Municipal, Employment Bureaus, 1918; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 6: Effect of Present Methods on Future Wage Adjustments, 1919; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 7: The Recent Trust Decisions, 1911; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 8: The Impatience Theory of Interest, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Unemployment: Problem and Remedies, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Reprints and Reports and Addresses of the National Conference of Charities and Correction, no.42.
  - Item 1: The Theory of The Minimun Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 2: The Theory of The Minimum Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 3: The New Anti-Trust Acts, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 4: Unemployment: Problem and Remedies, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 5: Coordination of Federal, State and Municipal, Employment Bureaus, 1918; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 6: Effect of Present Methods on Future Wage Adjustments, 1919; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 7: The Recent Trust Decisions, 1911; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 8: The Impatience Theory of Interest, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Coordination of Federal, State and Municipal, Employment Bureaus, 1918; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Reprinted from the American Economic Review Supplement, v.8:no.1 (1918:March)
  - Item 1: The Theory of The Minimun Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 2: The Theory of The Minimum Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 3: The New Anti-Trust Acts, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 4: Unemployment: Problem and Remedies, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 5: Coordination of Federal, State and Municipal, Employment Bureaus, 1918; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 6: Effect of Present Methods on Future Wage Adjustments, 1919; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 7: The Recent Trust Decisions, 1911; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 8: The Impatience Theory of Interest, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Effect of Present Methods on Future Wage Adjustments, 1919; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Reprinted from the Proceedings of the Academy of Political Science, v.8:no.2 (1919:Feb.)
  - Item 1: The Theory of The Minimun Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 2: The Theory of The Minimum Wage, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 3: The New Anti-Trust Acts, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 4: Unemployment: Problem and Remedies, 1915; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 5: Coordination of Federal, State and Municipal, Employment Bureaus, 1918; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 6: Effect of Present Methods on Future Wage Adjustments, 1919; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 7: The Recent Trust Decisions, 1911; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Item 8: The Impatience Theory of Interest, 1912; Publication (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Notes to lecture in Political Economy delivered by Professor Ely., 1890; Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Johns Hopkins University. October 1, 1890. Bound.
  - Item 1: Notes to lecture in Political Economy delivered by Professor Ely., 1890; Publication (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Notes: Johns Hopkins University. October 1, 1890. Bound.
- Henry Rogers Seager, 1870-1930, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Reprinted from the Columbia University Quarterly, Dec. 1930.
  - Item 1: Company Unions vs. Trade Unions, 1923; Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 2: Henry Rogers Seager, 1930; Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Item 3: Henry Rogers Seager, 1870-1930, Publication (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Images digitized from the collection., Publication (Box 2)